Roy Leeper and Gaylord Hall collection of Miné Okubo Papers, circa 1940-2001, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Roy Leeper and Gaylord Hall collection of Miné Okubo papers
circa 1940-2001
Archives of American Art
Okubo, Miné, 1912-2001
AAA.okubmine
Archival Resource Key
1.4 Linear feet
The Roy Leeper and Gaylord Hall collection of Miné Okubo papers measure 1.4 linear feet and date from circa 1940 to 2001. Roy Leeper and Gaylord Hall were long-time friends with and patrons of Okubo from the late 1950s until her death. The collection contains letters, writings, and sketches by Okubo. Among the printed materials is a copy of the 1944 special edition of Fortune magazine which was sympathetic to Japanese Americans interned during World War II and for which Okubo was hired to illustrate. Also found are scattered documents relating to Hall and Leeper.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 7 series.
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1942-1994 (1 folder; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1957-2001 (0.8 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, circa 1940-circa 1970 (3 folders; Box 1)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, 1957-1998 (0.1 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1944-2000 (0.3 linear feet; Boxes 1-3)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1940-circa 1990s (3 folders; Box 1)
Series 7: Artwork, 1960s-1997 (0.1 linear feet; Boxes 1-2)
Biographical / Historical
Miné Okubo (1912-2001) was a Japanese American painter, illustrator, and author. She is known for her book Citizen 13600 in which she described her experience at the Topaz War Relocation Camp in Utah through prose and drawings.
Born in Riverside, California in 1912, Okubo began her arts education at Riverside Junior College and transferred to the University of California, Berkeley where she completed her BA and MA in Fine Arts (where she first met Roy Leeper). In 1938, she received an award to travel and study under Fernand Léger in Paris. When World War II began in Europe, she moved back to California and worked under the Federal Arts Project. She produced some solo murals and also assisted Diego Rivera on his Treasure Island mural Pan American Unity, (1940).
In April of 1942, Miné Okubo and one of her brothers were sent to the Tanforan Assembly Center under Executive Order 9066, which forcibly interned over 100,000 Japanese and Japanese-American citizens living on the West Coast of the United States. Six months later, they were sent to the Topaz War Relocation Camp in Topaz, Utah. There, Okubo taught art in the camp's school and often sketched camp life. She was art editor for the camp newsletter Trek, a supplement to the Topaz Times.
In 1944, Fortune magazine published a sympathetic special edition on the Japanese and Japanese American internment during World War II. The magazine hired Okubo to illustrate two of the articles. She was permitted to leave the camp and move to New York City, where she remained for the rest of her life, working as a painter and illustrator. She wrote and illustrated a book about her experiences in the Topaz confinement camp, Citizen 13600, which won the American Book Award in 1984. Miné Okubo died in 2001. Medical doctor Roy Leeper befriended Miné Okubo while they were both students at the University of California. Later, he and his partner dentist Gaylord Hall were reintroduced to Okubo and her artwork by a mutual friend. They began a life-long relationship with Okuba, both as friends and collectors.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Roy Leeper and Gaylord Hall donated the collection of Miné Okubo papers in 2001.
Scope and Contents
The Roy Leeper and Gaylord Hall collection of Miné Okubo papers measure 1.4 linear feet and date from circa 1940 to 2001. Roy Leeper and Gaylord Hall were long-time friends with and patrons of Okubo from the late 1950s until her death. The collection contains letters, writings, and sketches by Okubo. Among the printed materials is a copy of the 1944 special edition of Fortune magazine which was sympathetic to Japanese Americans interned during World War II and for which Okubo was hired to illustrate. Also found are scattered documents relating to Hall and Leeper.
Biographical materials consist of Roy Leeper's medical licenses. The bulk of the collection is comprised of Miné Okubo's letters, many of which are illustrated, to Hall and Leeper discussing her health, career, their purchase of her artwork, and mutual friends. Other correspondents include Howard Hamilton and Doris and Harry Tono. Writings and notes by Okubo inlcude a statement about the pricing of her artwork and a list of artwork. Leeper and Hall's personal business records concern the purchase and loan of Okubo's artwork for exhibitions.
Printed materials include a 1944 edition of Fortune magazine devoted to the internment of Japanese Americans during World War II. The issue includes reproductions of Okubo's illustrations of life in the World War II internment camp in Topaz, Utah. Photographs include snapshots of Okubo at an exhibition with her art and of works of art. Sketches and drawings depict mostly cats and flowers.
Related Materials
Riverside City College in Riverside, California also holds the Miné Okubo papers.
Photographs; Women artists; Art patronage; Drawings; Sketches; Illustrated letters; Asian American art; Asian American artists; Japanese American art; Japanese American artists; Asian American painters; Asian American illustrators; Asian American authors; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Illustrators -- New York (State) -- New York; Authors -- New York (State) -- New York; Women painters; Women illustrators; Women authors; Japanese Americans -- Forced removal and internment -- 1942-1945; Central Utah Relocation Center; Hall, Gaylord; Tono, Harry; Tono, Doris; Leeper, Roy; Hamilton, Howard
- Biographical Material, 1942-1994; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 1 Folder Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical materials include Dr. Roy Leeper's medical licenses from the states of Virginia and California.
  - Medical Licenses, Roy Leeper, 1942-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1957-2001; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.8 Linear feet Box 1
  The bulk of this series consists of letters from Miné Okubo to Gaylord Hall and Roy Leeper. Many of the letters begin by mentioning her mood or health and she often inquires about the health and activities of Hall and Leeper and their mutual friends, although they do not tend to be overly personal. Okubo references her artistic process, specific artworks purchased by or of interest to Hall and Leeper, and acknowledges receipt of payment for a work of art. Many of the letters are illustrated in pen or colored pencil.
  There is also one letter from Leeper to Okubo; a letter to Howard Hamilton; and scattered letters between Doris and Harry Tono, Okubo, and Leeper and Hall.
  Arrangement
  Some letters greet both Roy Leeper and Gaylord Hall in the letter but are addressed to one on the envelope; those letters are organized based on the addressed envelope.
  - Miné Okubo to Gaylord Hall, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Miné Okubo to Gaylord Hall, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Miné Okubo to Gaylord Hall, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Miné Okubo to Gaylord Hall, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Miné Okubo to Gaylord Hall, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miné Okubo to Gaylord Hall, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Miné Okubo to Gaylord Hall, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Miné Okubo to Gaylord Hall, circa 1960-circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Miné Okubo to Howard Hamilton, 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1973 Jan-Oct; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1973 Nov-Dec; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1974 Jan-Mar; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1974 Jun-Dec; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Miné Okubo to Roy Leeper, circa 1957-circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Roy Leeper to Miné Okubo, 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Miné Okubo to Doris and Harry Tono, 1987-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Doris and Harry Tono to Gaylord Hall and Roy Leeper, 1998-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Writings and Notes, circa 1940-1970; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 3 Folders Box 1
  Writings by Miné Okubo include a statement concerning the pricing for her artwork and a list of works of art. There is also one note, likely written by Roy Leeper.
  - Statement on Pricing, by Okubo, circa 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - List of Works of Art, circa 1960-circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Note, likely by Leeper, circa 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Personal Business Records, 1957-1998; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Personal business records mostly concern Roy Leeper's and Gaylord Hall's purchase and loan of artwork by Miné Okubo. There are price lists; receipts and statements for payments received by Okubo, many of which mention specific works of art; and records from loans of their Miné Okubo artwork to the San Francisco Museum of Art and the Oakland Museum of Art for exhibition. A certificate of authenticity is for a Japanese ivory figurine, although it is not clear who owned the piece.
  - Certificate of Authenticity, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Exhibition and Loan Records, Oakland Museum of Art, 1995-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Exhibition and Loan Records, San Francisco Museum of Art, 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Price List, circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Receipts, 1966-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Statements, 1963-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 61)
- Printed Material, 1944-2000; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Boxes 1-3
  Printed materials concern Okubo's career as an artist and writer, including her experiences in the World War II Japanese American confinement camp in Topaz, Utah. There is a brochure and program for award events, clippings, a publication in Japanese concerning Executive Order 9066, exhibition announcements, issues of periodicals; and a poster featuring Okubo as a courageous California woman. Also found is the 1944 issue of Fortune magazine featuring Okubo's illustrations for two articles, "Issei, Nisei, Kibei" and "The Citizen-Subject...Tightens His Belt and Wipes Off His Smile."
  - Award Publications, 1974-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Clippings, 1972-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Executive Order 9066, circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1980-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 65)
    Oversized material housed in Box 2, F1
  - Fortune Magazine, 1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 66)
    Oversized material housed in Box 2, F3
  - National Japanese American Historical Society, Nikkei Heritage, 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Poster, circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 68)
    Oversized material housed in OV3
  - Oversized Exhibition Announcement from Box 1, F65, 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Magazine from Box 1, F66, 1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Poster from Box 1, F68, circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 3)
- Photographs, circa 1940-circa 1990s; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 3 Folders Box 1
  Photographs are of Miné Okubo with her art at an exhibition; portraits of Roy Leeper or Gaylord Hall; and photographs of Okubo's works of art.
  - Miné Okubo, at an Exhibition, circa 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - of Roy Leeper or Gaylord Hall, circa 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Works of Art, circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 71)
- Artwork, 1960s-1997; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Found here are Okubo's painted sketches and drawings depicting cats and flowers, some of which may have been used for her holiday cards.
  - Paintings and Drawings, by Okubo, circa 1960s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Prints, by Okubo, 1977-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 73)
    Oversized material housed in Box 2, F2
  - Oversized Prints from Box 1, F73, circa 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)